Guide to the Harold Albert Wilson Papers, 1898-1965 MS 303
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Harold Albert Wilson Papers
1898-1965
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Wilson, Harold A. (Harold Albert)
MS 303
3 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
This collection contains the papers of Harold Albert Wilson who was the first professor of physics at Rice Institute. Included are: Wilson's scientific papers (off-prints only); manuscript of bibliography of the H. A. Wilson scientific papers; "Catalogue of Apparatus," photographs, certificates, and letters to Norman Hurd Ricker.
Biographical Sketch
Harold Albert Wilson was born in York, England on December 1, 1874. Wilson's interest in engines and machines came from playing with a working model of a railway locomotive his father gave him about the time he entered kindergarten. Under the influence of his father, he began to experiment with chemistry at an early age when Wilson received Bloxham's Chemistry from him and bought a box of chemical apparatus from a pawnshop. Later, Wilson taught himself glass blowing which he admitted helped him in much of his research.
He graduated from a private preparatory school called St. Olave's at age 17 but stayed on as a mathematics teacher for two years. Afterward, he attended Victoria University in Leeds where he studied mathematics, physics, chemistry and biology. Wilson received first class honors in chemistry in the London intermediate B.Sc. and scholarships from both London and Leeds for two years. Three years later, Wilson obtained a first class in the ordinary London B.Sc. in applied mathematics, chemistry, and physics. While studying in college, he was able to conduct more research and published a small paper in the Chemical News on the size of atoms. He also worked with professors at Cambridge on the conductivity of flames containing salts. In 1897, he decided to work under J. J. Thomson at the Cavendish at Cambridge for a research degree which he received in 1899. Afterward, Wilson went to Berlin to work in a laboratory until he received the Allen Scholarship to go back to Cambridge eight months later. In 1901, he was awarded the Clerk Maxwell Studentship and elected to a Fellowship in Trinity College. In 1904, he received a vacant Lectureship at King's College in London where he was soon appointed as Chair. From the Principal, Wilson was able to receive money to increase the space for research at King's College. In 1906, Wilson was elected as a Fellow of the Royal Society. In 1909, he accepted a professorship in Applied Physics at McGill University in Montreal.
In 1912, the new Rice Institute of Houston, TX offered Wilson a Professorship which he took partly because he was interested in helping to start a new university. At that time, the physics department was temporarily housed in the mechanical building until 1914 the physics building proper was finished under Wilson's supervision. It came with an apparatus and teaching cost of several hundred thousand dollars. During WWI, Wilson assisted the United States Navy as a technical expert on anti-submarine devices. Wilson invented binaural listening devices for locating submarines. He published a paper at New London, CT which provided much insight on sound receivers. Shortly after accepting his position at Rice Institute, Wilson married Marjorie Patterson Smyth, who was a gold-medalist in mathematics and physics at McGill, by whom he had two sons and two daughters.
Wilson quickly gained a high reputation as a teacher at Rice and established a research school which also gained a high reputation as it grew. In 1925, he left Rice Institute for Chair of Natural Philosophy in Glasgow; however, the pensions offered at British universities were not satisfying to Wilson's needs so he accepted President Lovett's offer to come back to Rice. He was offered his professorship back which also came with a position as a consultant physicist to Humble Oil and Refining Co. He was naturalized as a U.S. citizen in 1931. During World War II, Wilson was one of the senior scientists to develop the atomic bomb in Chicago.
Wilson was appraised as an excellent teacher by both his colleagues and students. He also enjoyed teaching immensely and was loved by his students. He retired in 1947, at age 70 but continued teaching a small class out of his home in special and general relativity until his late 80's. Wilson's work was a contribution to the development of Rice Institute to a University making Rice an important center for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the papers of Harold Albert Wilson who was the first professor of physics at Rice Institute. Wilson was best known for his work on flames which continued to be his primary interest throughout his life. Included are: Wilson's scientific papers (off-prints only); manuscript of bibliography of the H. A. Wilson scientific papers; "Catalogue of Apparatus," photographs, certificates, awards, news clippings and letters to Norman Hurd Ricker, first person to hold three Rice degrees.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Access Restrictions
This materials is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Letters were a gift of Mrs. Norman Hurd Ricker on May 14, 1980. The bound volumes were transferred from the Rice University Archives on July 10, 1980.
Related Materials
Another Joan Wilson Scrapbook, "Rice Institute Doings 1933--" can be found in the Rice University Scrapbook collection.
Index Terms
Subjects
Physics; Universities and colleges
Subjects (Persons)
Wilson, Harold A. (Harold Albert)
- Series I: Academic Papers, 1898-1960, 44238
  - Loose-leaf notebook which includes Wilson's mathematical notes, ca. 1960., 44242 (Box 1)
  - "Scientific Papers of Harold Albert Wilson"- includes all of Wilson's published notes and articles, 1898-1952., 44241 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of the bibliography of the H.A.W. Scientific Papers., 44240 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Catalogue of Apparatus" 1909, 44239 (Box 2)
- Series II: Newspaper clippings and monographs, 1912-1965, 44235
  - Clippings- News of Wilson's arrival to Houston, public lectures, accomplishments, and obituary., 44237 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Monographs, 1965- short biographies of Wilson plus a copy of the The Rice Engineer, Winter 1965 which is a dedication to H.A. Wilson and his career., 44236 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III: Photographs and ID cards, 1900-1962, 44233
  - Photographs and ID Registration cards- includes images of Wilson accepting the Medal of Honor and Certificate of Merit from Rice University President Dr. Kenneth S. Pitzer and ID cards issued to Wilson when he worked for the U. S. Navy at New London, CT in 1918., 44234 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Correspondence, 1917-1963, 44231
  - Correspondence between Norman Hurd Ricker and Wilson. Plus, correspondence between Wilson and publishers., 44232 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series V: Certificates and Awards, 1900-1962, 44229
  - Includes Doctor of Science degree received from the University of London in 1900 and the Certificate of Merit from Rice University in 1962. There are also numerous certificates Wilson received from honor societies such as the Royal Philosophical Society of Philadelphia and Phi Beta Kappa Fraternity., 44230 (Box 3)
- Series VI. Scrapbook
  - Joan Wilson scrapbook, 1932-1933 (Box 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Joan Wilson daughter of H.A. Wilson scrapbook for her senior year in high school at San Jacinto High School and attendance at St. Mary's School and Junior College in Raleigh, North Carolina.